Nathanael Greene Papers 1777-1780 Mss.B.G83
American Philosophical Society
- Series I: Correspondence, 1777-1780; 3 lin. feet
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 22; 1p.; Claiborne, Richard (Box 1)
    West Point - Maryland division waiting for their clothing. Mr. Belding wishes to know if his assistance is necessary in quartering the light dragoons at Wallingsford.
    ix, 28
  - to Burnside, 1779 June 21; 2pp.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging letter of the 14th and 15th insts. to Gen. Greene. Certain directions from Gen. Greene relative to the route the provisions must take.
    vi, 87
  - to James F. Abeel, 1779 September 13; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - Acknowledging his favor of 6th inst. to Gen. Greene. A Court of Inquiry ordered at Morristown to investigate the business and charges between Col. Claiborne and Mr. Lewis. Desires him to pay Mr. Collis his wages.
    iv, 24
  - to Benjamin Stoddert, 1779 September 13; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - Directed by Gen. Greene to acknowledge his favor of the 18th inst. with the enclosed resolve of Congress for erecting barracks at Rhode Island. The General has given the necessary orders agreeable to the resolution.
    viii, 15
  - to Jacob Weiss, 1779 September 13; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    Acknowledging favor of the 3d inst. Directions regarding the return of stores.
    ix, 25
  - to John Cox, 1779 September 16; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - The army is to be cantoned and the greater part to quarter at the Scotch Plains. Gen. Greene requests him to have 200,000 feet of boards deposited at some convenient place in that neighborhood with dispatch and secrecy.
    ix, 26
  - to William Betts, 1779 September 17; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - Acknowledging his favor of same date. General wishes him to propose to the shipwrights to continue a week longer upon their present standing; but if they decline, to discharge them.
    iii, 47
  - to William Betts, 1779 September 19; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - Acknowledging favor of 18th inst. The General only wants the carpenters engaged for one week more. If at the end of that time, no further directions are received, he can discharge them.
    iii, 48
  - to Col. Thompson, 1779 September 29; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    West Point - In answer to his favor to Gen. Green, dated the 30th of September, asks him to furnish the twelve wagons and teams called for from the line of the army of from the Commissary's department.
    iv, 12
  - to John Cox, 1779 November 5; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    Directed by Gen. Greene to write him to procure the cloth for the bags, but not to have them made until he hears further from the General.
    viii, 16
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 5; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    By Gen. Greene's order, writes to direct him to send all the unemployed carpenters to West Point and to send Capt. Mills with his company to King's Ferry.
    ix, 27
  - to James Thompson, 1779 November 11; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    Directs him, by Gen. Greene's orders, to be at Fishkill the following day to attend a horse sale, and to purchase wagon and express horses. Has referred the Auditor of Accounts to him for two teams.
    viii, 17
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    In Gen. Greene's behalf, acknowledges his favor of same date enclosing copy of a letter from Col. Van de Burgh, respecting the wages of express-riders. They are allowed $ 16 a day, find their own horses and bear their own expenses. Demand for boards at King's Ferry.
    viii, 18
  - to George Gray, n.d.; 1p.; Claiborne, Robert (Box 1)
    Order to shoe Dr. Thatcher's horse.
    xii, 90
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 27; 1p.; Clark, Thomas (Box 1)
    Paramus - In future will send weekly returns. Wants tents for his soldiers.
    ix, 29
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 7; 1p.; Clay, M. (Box 1)
    Orders to repair Charles Carter's gun.
    xii, 73
  - to George Morgan, 1779 April 20; 1p.; Clinton, Charles, 1739-1812 (Box 2)
    Fort Cumberland - Has opened the road from the above place to Turkey Foot, except four of five miles. Money needed to pay hands. Enclosing survey. (Copy)
    vii, 20a
  - to James McDowel, 1779 January 12; 1p.; Clinton, George (Box 2)
    Poughkeepsie - Informing him that Gen. Washington will lay his case before Congress, who will no doubt order an equitable compensation for his loss. (Copy)
    i, 15
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 28; 1p.; Clinton, George (Box 2)
    Smith's Clove - Col. Hay in immediate want of about $ 100,000; begs the Governor to loan that sum to the department, promising to replace it in a week or two in the treasury. Most of the money to be appropriated for the Indian expedition. Col. Hay will wait upon him for an answer.
    vi, 97
  - to Udny Hay, 1779 November 8; 3p.; Clinton, George (Box 2)
    Fishkill - Acknowledging favor of equal date concerning the present dispute of the artificers about their wages. If the representation made by them to the Governor is true, he thinks their demands are reasonable. How far it will be proper to comply with these demands, declines to determine.
    ix, 55
  - to Robert Forsyth, 1779 January 2; 1p.; Colfax, William (Box 2)
    Headquarters - Applies to him once again for six pounds of nails and fifteen boards.
    viii, 19
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 2pp.; Collins, Stephen, ca. 1758-1794 (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Setting forth the case of Sarah Whitbread who, having obtained a pass to New York, was on her way back with sundry goods, which were taken from her by an American officer who gave her a receipt for them. Most of the articles intended as presents for Mrs. Collins. Ask for some redress.
    iv, 14
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 1p.; Collins, Stephen, ca. 1758-1794 (Box 2)
    A list of sundry goods belonging to Mrs. Whitbread, stopped by Capt. Stokes, commanding officers at B. Town. Enclosed with previous letter.
    iv, 15
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 27; 1p.; Cooper, Constant et. al. (Box 2)
    Thanking Gen. Greene for his care in securing the property of the public.
    i, 94
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 4; 1p.; Cotton, John (Box 2)
    Croton River - Desiring to know the duties and privileges attached to the office of Brigade Quartermaster, in order to settle on or two disputed points.
    vii, 33
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 11; 1p.; Cotton, John (Box 2)
    Middletown - Acknowledging his favor of 26th utl. together with Gen. Washington's to Moses bush, requesting him to procure a number of scows. Has put his carpenters to work on them and is pushing the work through.
    viii, 20
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Will inquire into the prices of pack-saddles, and if they can be had at 3 pounds will order 500 of them. Dispatched an express to Col. Patterson and will accompany him to camp on his arrival. Mrs. Cox and family send compliments to Mrs. Greene.
    iv, 16
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 16; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Just honored with his favor of that morning and sends the horse by bearer. Congress has received some very interesting intelligence, which is affected to be kept a profound secret. Many conjectures as to its nature. Has had a considerable effect in reducing prices. Pennsylvania's tax bill under consideration. Report of five or six of the enemy's armed vessels being carried into Chesapeake bay by two Continental frigates. Intelligence received that the schooner Hunter has brought in a prize.
    iv, 17
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 18; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Expects Col. Patterson by Saturday or Sunday at farthest, when he will be able to accompany him.
    iv, 18
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 8; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Mount Holly - Acknowledging favor of 6th inst. Flatters himself that the articles ordered to be deposited at Estherton are there, and those for Fort Pitt are on their way up. Unable to say when wagons, horses, etc., requisite to enable His Excellency to make a general movement of the army, can be in readiness. Expects to have a handsome supply of teams, etc., at camp by the middle of May. Every possible exertion being made by himself and all his deputies. Sudden death of his brother, Mr. William Cox.
    vii, 49
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 10; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 6th inst. Has given orders to every deputy in his department to forward wagons, horses or stores of any kind to camp. Detailing the different articles needed and where he is procuring them. Difficulty in obtaining watermen on the Susquehanna. Col. Davis' report of what he is able to send. Col. Pettit distressed by demands on him, which multiply hourly.
    vii, 65
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 11; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 10th inst. Will write to agents countermanding orders, but fears it will not be in time. Every possible exertion has been made to expedite the Indian Expedition. Number of tents, etc., sent by Col. Mitchell. Will forward them to camp unless otherwise directed.
    vii, 69
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 11; 4pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 10th inst. With enclosures. Reasons for the major's objections to the pack-saddles. Thinks himself that they are superior to those made by Col. Hooper. Quality of axes ordered. Stores from Philadelphia as good as those procured elsewhere. Best write for pack-saddles. Promises every exertion in raising bateau-men.
    vii, 70
  - Extract of letter to..., 1779 May 11; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Easton - Acknowledging letter of 10th inst., which he laid before Gen. Sullivan. Gen. Sullivan's wishes concerning the pack-saddles.
    vii, 87
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 18; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Enclosing invoice of stores going and gone. Amount of supplies furnished by Col. Mitchell. Col. Davis writes of the scarcity of forage. Wages of boatmen engaged by Col. Morgan. Boats cannot proceed up the river without a sufficient guard to defend them. and there is not a soldier there for that purpose. Asks for advice about horses sent to Mr. Furman who has no forage for them. Road to be opened across the great swamp to Wyoming. Fears that unless spirited measures are taken the populace are likely to think the Staff department composed of rascals. Maj. Blodget weather-bound at Bloomsbury, diverting the ladies on the spinet.
    v, 21
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 19; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Will procure and send forward stores for Col. Hay. Obliged to give $ 6.00 a day for bateaumen. Hopes to be with him in a day or two, ashe is now quite strong.
    v, 31
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 21; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 20th inst. Ordered Mr. Mitchell to Forward 200 portmanteaus to Easton with all possible dispatch. Canteens had better be ordered from Middlebrook. Other articles sent.
    v, 48
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 31; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Has hurried on the wagons. Will set out for Philadelphia early the next morning, from which town hopes to sent portmanteaus and tents in plenty.
    vi, 24
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 6; 4pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Ringwood - Enemy's designs difficult to interpret from his movements; they have fallen back to King's Ferry again, after being in full view of the fortifications at West Point, without attempting to make any impression upon the works. Loss of a little of fort by Gen. McDougall on the east side of King's Ferry. Enemy's purpose to cut off their communication with the Eastern States. Difficulty of subsisting their cattle and keeping up the necessary transportation through such a barren country. Plans for subsisting the troops in case West Point is invested, and for transporting provisions and forage. Necessity for removing clothing at Middlebrook as fast as possible to somewhere back of Morristown.
    vi, 27
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 9; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Camp, Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging favor of 5th inst. Will rest satisfied in full expectation of plentiful supply of stores. Will lay his letter before the General in order to have an officer appointed to the command of the watermen; conflicting accounts from that quarter. Directions as to forwarding the store back into the country from Middlebrook. Enemy making no attempt on West Point, but fortifying King's Ferry.
    vi, 37
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 14; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Smith's Tavern - Business of enlisting wagoners must be pursued with more vigor; if hey cannot be had at the present rate of payment, it must be raised.
    vi, 65
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 20; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Smith's Tavern - Desiring him to make such arrangements at Middlebrook as will render Col. Thomson's further stay there unnecessary. Will change position again immediately if enemy fall across the river. Needs of the Eastern army.
    vi, 80
  - Circular letter to Q.M. Deputies, 1779 July 8; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Circular letter to the deputies in the Quartermaster department to the westward of the Delaware, asking for a general return.
    x, 18
  - to John Davis, 1779 July 28; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 24th inst. Gen. Hand's extraordinary demand for horses to transport stores to Wyoming. Cannot consent to Col. Davis' complying with such a request.
    ix, 30
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 2; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Acknowledging letter of 26th ult. Has prevailed on Major Eyre to join the army whenever Gen. Greene thinks his presence necessary. Number and destination of the flat-bottomed boats on hand. Wishes to know if more shall be built. Desires the earliest intelligence of the arrival of the French fleet, that he may join Gen. Greene before he enters the city. Great rise in the price of provisions, foreign and domestic.
    iii, 27
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 6; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Acknowledging favor of 27th ult. List of boats sent up to Trenton. More, if wanted, can be built at Easton. Department in great distress for want of cash. Gen. Greene's winter boats in hand. Gen. Knox's saddle will be sent as soon as it can be made.
    iii, 23
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 10; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Philadelphia - Informing him that Major Eyre, at the head of about 100 well-disposed carpenters, intends setting out for headquarters Tuesday morning. Puzzled to know how to raise enough cash to give them each a monthly advance. Terrible demand for cash. Difficulty in procuring canvas for tents; enumerates the number sent on and promises more. Stoves being made as fast as possible. Fast sailing boats, ordered by His Excellency, waiting for the dispatches to Count d'Estaing.
    iii, 22a
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 20; 4pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of the 13th inst. Disposition he has made of the flat-bottomed boats. Best route for the boats to take on the Susquehanna. Number of boats nearly sufficient. Badly off for tents and forage; no canvas for the first and no money for the second. Constant demands for cash and not a shilling to be got from the Treasury. Thinks it high time that they should come to a full and complete explanation with Congress. Tremendous rise in the price of boards, forage, etc. Count d'Estaing's success; no particulars as yet. Wagon hire.
    iii, 22
  - to Robert Patton, 1779 October 20; 1p.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Enclosing a long list of articles wanted in the Quartermaster department for the next campaign. Begging him to get the best materials and have them ready to forward to camp by April 1.
    ii, 2 and 3
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 23; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 20th inst., and promising to do his best as regard tents. Black outlook as regards cash. Arguments of no effect with the Treasury. Arrival of thirteen boats; will direct Col. Berry to detain them at the White House until he receives order what to do with them. Lack of forage, owing to Major Gordon not being supplied with money. Cannot make provision for the next campaign without cash.
    iii, 34
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 2; 3pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 26th ult. from Gen. Greene (?). Number and destination of boats. Reason for ship-carpenters' high wages; advises their dismissal. Good prospect of procuring tents. Has ordered to Morristown every article needed for hutting the troops. Col. Biddle over head and ears in debt.
    ix, 31
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 7; 7pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 30th ult. Obliged for the agreeable intelligence of the evacuation of Newport. Measures taken for the safety of boards and forage. Prospect for tents has brightened. Gen. Sullivan's want of economy. Present difficulties in the various departments, owing to lack of money. Begs Gen. Greene to take a peremptory and spirited attitude towards Congress. Disposition of boats. Col. Pettit hastening the settlement of accounts; he has taken a house in Philadelphia; says his prospects for cash were never worse. Scattered situation of boats built in Susquehanna. No prospect of getting forage.
    ix, 32
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 17; 4pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Sand bags in readiness. Congratulates him on the arrival of Mrs. Greene. Unless effectual measures are immediately taken to open the eyes of the Treasury and induce them to furnish a very considerable sum to the Quartermaster department, supplies expected from his quarter must assuredly cease. Mr. Pettit only received a small fraction of the cash needed. Suggests the immediate surrender of all appointments and offices, to arouse those at the helm to a sense of their duty. Desires information respecting the boats, also the troops' winter quarters. Mr. Pettit's opinion, and his also, that money will soon be more valuable than any article at the present price. Mr. Pettit's plan, therefore, to turn all their concerns in shipping into cash.
    ix, 33
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 23; 2pp.; Cox, John, 1731-1793 (Box 2)
    Bloomsbury - Acknowledging favor of 20th inst. Mr. Furman's report on the number of boards deposited at various towns. All efforts to get a supply of cash from the Treasury, fruitless. Money depreciated twenty-five per cent., since there repulse at Savannah. has given the necessary directions concerning the craft in the Susquehanna.
    ix, 34
  - to George Gray, 1779 April 10; 1p.; Croghan, William, 1752-1823 (Box 2)
    Order to repair the bearer's gun, which he has had for two or three weeks.
    xii, 77
  - to George Gray, n.d.; 1p.; Croghan, William, 1752-1823 (Box 2)
    Order for an iron rod to be made for his portmanteau.
    xii, 110
  - to George Gray, 1778 October 27; 1p.; Dabney, Charles (Box 2)
    Order to repair a gun belonging to Thomas Collier.
    xii, 91
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 10; 2pp.; Davis, John, 1755-1783 (Box 2)
    Carlisle - Acknowledging favor of 2d inst. Directions respecting tents shall be strictly complied with. Alterations in pack-saddles. Frightened to death about scarcity of forage and difficulty of procuring wagons. Stores and packhorses to be sent forward.
    vii, 100
  - to Charles Pettit, 1779 May 21; 3pp.; Davis, John, 1755-1783 (Box 2)
    Carlisle - Acknowledging favor of 14th inst. with $ 300,000. Demands on him for wagons and how he meets them. Scarcity of forage. Difficulty of getting drivers; need not expect one, unless they are exempted from militia duty.
    v, 47
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 30; 2pp.; Davis, John, 1755-1783 (Box 2)
    Carlisle - Informing him of the number of horses purchased and the time at which he may expect them. Must pay drivers same wages as boatmen, in order to get them. Account of stores forwarded.
    v, 100
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 16; 2pp.; Deputies of the Quartermaster's Department [Circular Letter] (Box 2)
    Smith's Tavern - Enclosing a copy of a letter from hon. John Dickinson, Roger Sherman, Nathaniel Scudder, Esqs., members of Congress, a committee appointed for superintending the staff department of the army. Explains the design of this letter and also the returns expected of them in reply. Committee anxious to have this information without the least unnecessary delay.
    vi, 73
  - from Nathanael Greene, 1779 June 13; 2pp.; Dickinson, John, Roger Sherman, and Nathaniel Scudder (Box 2)
    Smith's Tavern - Acknowledging favor of 7th inst. Promising to furnish them with the returns and information concerning the plan and economy of the quartermaster's department. Requests punctuality in the returns.
    vi, 58
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 May 27; 1p.; Duportail, Luis (Box 2)
    Camp - Requesting orders for wagons, tents, blankets, etc.
    v, 78
  - to Andrew Coldclugh, 1p.; Durie, Thomas (Box 2)
    Orders from Gen. Greene not to deliver any forage to Capt. Prior of the artillery.
    ii, 37
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 6; 1p.; Eastham, Braxton (Box 2)
    Order to shoe the bearer's horse.
    xii, 84
  - to George Gray, 1778 December 29; 1p.; Eastham, Braxton (Box 2)
    Order to shoe four horses belonging to Gen. Muhlenberg's brigade.
    xii, 96
  - to Jacob Shallus, 1779 March 24; 1p.; Eichelberger, George (Box 2)
    York - Asking him to send a quantity of salt.
    vii, 7
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 February 11; 1p.; Erskine, John (Box 2)
    Raritan - Writes on behalf of Mr. Weiss, who complains that a private road used by the soldiers leads past the two houses where the stores are deposited, and that two sentries are not sufficient to guard them. Wishes that road stopped, as the public road is equally convenient for the soldiers.
    iv, 19
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 October 5; 1p.; Erskine, John (Box 2)
    Murder's Creek - Has just received his letter concerning the clothing and letters that McDonald Campbell brought from Mrs. Greene. Never saw either clothes or dispatches, though he remembers consenting to Campbell's request that his dispatches might go by some of the expresses who were to leave the next morning for West Point.
    iii, 33
  - to Maj. Claiborne, 1779 November 8; 1p.; Erskine, John (Box 2)
    Mr. Southerland's - Enclosing last weekly report. Asking him to sign the blank appointments and send them up at once. Wants to know the charges against Van Court, whom Col. Claiborne has confined; thinks he can assist in the evidence against him.
    ix, 35
  - to George Olney, 1779 November 15; 1p.; Erskine, John (Box 2)
    New Cornwall - Enclosing last weekly report; asks him to tell the General that after strict inquiry into the expenses of the express-riders, he finds they will all be willing to stay at $ 20.00 per day.
    xii, 9
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 November 18; 1p.; Erskine, Robert, 1735-1780 (Box 2)
    New Windsor - In consequence of a not from Col. Morris, has dispatched Mr. Lodge, one of his surveyors, to Morristown; will endeavor to follow himself as soon as possible.
    ix, 36
  - to Nathanael Greene, 1779 December 18; 1p.; Erskine, Robert, 1735-1780 (Box 2)